<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sighes of Fraunce for the death of their late King, Henry the fourth The true maner of his murther: the forme of the coronation of Prince Lewes at S. Augustines. With the oration made by Mounsier Seruin, attourney generall to the King, exhorting both the peeres and people to alleageance. Printed in the Kings Palace.</title>
            <title>Souspirs de la France, sur la mort du roy Henry IIII. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103969</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839711</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839711</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4158</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03001)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4158)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 727:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sighes of Fraunce for the death of their late King, Henry the fourth The true maner of his murther: the forme of the coronation of Prince Lewes at S. Augustines. With the oration made by Mounsier Seruin, attourney generall to the King, exhorting both the peeres and people to alleageance. Printed in the Kings Palace.</title>
                  <title>Souspirs de la France, sur la mort du roy Henry IIII. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Windet?] for Iohn Budge, and are to be solde at his shoppe at Britaines Bursse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The murther of the French King.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Title page in pen facsimile.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIII, --  King of France, 1601-1643 --  Coronation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610 --  Assassination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4158:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <p>The ſighes of Fraunce for the death of their late King, HENRY the fourth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The true maner of his Murther: The forme of the Coronation of Prince</hi> LEWES <hi>at S. Auguſtines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the Oration made by Mounſier <hi>Seruin,</hi> Attourney generall to the King, exhorting both the Peeres and people to alleageance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in the Kings Palace.</hi> IOHN MORRIS.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a two-horse carriage, the driver holding a whip, in a mourning procession: two gentlemen are inside the coach, attended by a footman</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his Shoppe at Britaines Burſſe. 1610.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:4158:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:4158:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <head>
               <figure/>THE MVRTHER OF <hi>HENRY</hi> THE FOVRTH, THE LATE FRENCH KING.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Liege, I had made my ſelfe ready to write of the Pomps and Royalties at the Coronation of the Queene, from which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I am ſo altered, that I am at this time bound to ſpeake of the
<pb facs="tcp:4158:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
great griefe of Fraunce, and of the faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the French Nation. But it greeues me to repreſent that vnto you, which is too much in your memory: yet the King your father hath left ſuch an eſtimation of his life, that I cannot refuſe the laſt duties of my pen.</p>
            <p>It is true that there ſhould be an <hi>Apelles</hi> to paint worthily ſo great and conquering an <hi>Alexander<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and therfore I beare the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of his Palmes, to them that ſhall ſit downe to write of his victories? if there can be a pen found to flie as farre as the brute of his armes, and the renowne of them doth ſound. And if a tongue could haue as many good ſayings, as this Prince had va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and clemencie to conquer and pardon his enemies, how many tongues could be heard of your ſubiects, that haue felt the fruites of the peace, the which his courage procured them, and which his grace pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred them vnto? The remembrance of which, ſhould call them to come and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Toombe with their teares, and then
<pb facs="tcp:4158:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
render the teſtimonie of their faithfulneſſe to your Maieſtie, and beginning, by their plaints for their loſſes, an acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the lawfulneſſe of your ſucceſsion.</p>
            <p>My Liege, as the birds teſtifie by their ſilence the diſpleaſure they haue, by the loſſe of the ſunne, and how they doe ſalute the Spring, like reioycing Citizens with their melodious harmony; euen ſo your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects proue the iuſt ſorrowes that they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend by the death of his Maieſtie, and come at the beginning of your Reigne, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ioy, <hi>Viue le Roy,</hi> long Liue the king.</p>
            <p>And you, Lady, if you can promiſe to your ſelfe, that you may giue truce to your griefes, marke the loſſe of your Spouſe, and the zeale of the Princes of your kingdome, that hauing no ſooner ſeen the lying down of the king your husband, but are as ſoone come to ſalute the riſing vp of your ſonne, as their Soueraigne.</p>
            <p>The Princes (I do not name them) haue beene the firſt that haue offered him their ſwords, ſo recommendable are the effects
<pb facs="tcp:4158:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
that haue beene ſeene, vnder whoſe defence he is ſo ſtrengthned, they by him ſo ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; all France defended, that not a heart that neede to feare, if heauen doe not fall.</p>
            <p>The Officers of the Crowne, the Peeres of France, and all the noble French (that all other Nations may take example to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey their Prince) they haue witneſſed cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly, that death hath had no power to ſhake their conſtancie and fidelity.</p>
            <p>The chiefe of Iuſtice and the ſoueraigne Senate haue found &amp; acknowledge, that you ſhewed them pitty, when you had all might to commaund.</p>
            <p>And hee that hath the gouernment of policy, hath put order to diſorder, that where it did appeare, the whole world was reſolued to weepe for the dead Prince, they are now as ready to honour the liuing.</p>
            <p>And you Frenchmen, that are come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all parts, to ſee the Coronation of your Queene, are the eye-witneſſes of her eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, the which you haue beheld ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated in greater glory and pompe, then
<pb facs="tcp:4158:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
you could imagine, on Thurſday the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of May (according to the French computation) yet you haue ſeene her on Friday the fourteenth following, in a more violent affliction, then may be named or expreſſed.</p>
            <p>They then that had the curioſity to ſee her triumph on the one day, cannot chuſe but haue compaſsion, to behold her wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowhood on the next.</p>
            <p>But great calmes are euer the fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of great ſtormes. The Marriners are not proud to make their ſailes ſwell with a proſperous winde, neither looſe they their courage in the violence of tempeſt. So, as you haue looked with great modeſty on the Coronation of your Queene, regard her loſſe with conſtancie, and let the thought of obedience neuer ſlide from your duties; whereby it may appeare that the Vnion of France is a terror to all other Nations: that you can conquer, as well as fight, &amp; know how to giue law to your enemies with force, as you can take it from your king with humility.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4158:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->And that this may ſerue you as a proofe, that you haue had the moſt valiant king, the moſt mercifull, the moſt wiſe, and the moſt iudicious that euer was beloued of his people, feared of his enemies, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired of all the world: It is your duties, &amp; by your duty a benefit to deſire, that his Sonne ſucceede him in his perfections, as well as in his kingdomes; that the vertue of the Queene, eſtabliſhed as Regent in thoſe kingdomes, do ſupply the youth of the king, and he with her prudence make good to Fraunce the promiſes by the birth of a Son. In the meane time we ſhall endour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining for him, whoſe loſſe we begin to find, and tell this hiſtory to our poſterity.</p>
            <p>In Paris the chiefe city of France, whom al Prouinces doe owe homage vnto, for the meruailes which be found in her, being more properly to be termed, &amp; more ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to be found, a little world, then a great City; A miſerable Aſſaſin, and a damnable Parricide, borne at Angouleſme, named <hi>Francis Rauaillart,</hi> hath bereaued vs of the Father of our Patrimonie, taken away the
<pb facs="tcp:4158:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
Pearle of kings, and vndone vs of the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the world.</p>
            <p>This villaine, who hauing beene preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the violence of this fatall blow, and the fury of his intent in foure ſeuerall attempts, by the protection of the higheſt &amp; vigilance of his Guards, the Friday the fourteenth of May, waighting his opportunity, he found him in his Caroche in the end of the ſtreete of <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronnerie,</hi> who ſeeing the Caroche ſtayd by the meeting of a Caroche and a Cart, as the King ſhould paſſe, he came out of a ſhop, where he had kept himſelfe againſt the kings co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, although ſomewhat diſtracted in ſhewe of face before the attempt, and ſo came to the Caroche where his Maieſty was, &amp; as he was then in earneſt talke with other Peeres, who were then preſent in company with him, &amp; himſelfe dreadles of ſuch an imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, leaning on the Columne, hee gaue him two blowes with a knife, with ſo ſuddaine an executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the murther was ſooner found then the murtherer: yet in the end by diligent ſearch he was taken, and the king caried back to the Louu're, with the teares of the Lords, &amp; receaued with plaints at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming back.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4158:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->The Counſell roſe, all the City was in an vprore at this vntimely accident, while his Guards with a mournful diligence, came and yeelded themſelues before the Louu're, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue (&amp; be ordred by) the commandements of the Counſell, which appointed vnto them this eſpeciall charge, that they ſhould let none paſſe but the Princes of the bloud, &amp; men of eminent place. Then came the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and Court of Guard, offering volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily both their Armes and liues, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine &amp; mourne the moſt monſtrous mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their deceaſed king, and for the firme eſtabliſhing of the liuing Prince his ſonne.</p>
            <p>On Saterday the fifteenth of May (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the French computation) the young Prince <hi>Lewes</hi> the thirteenth, and of the off-ſpring of S. <hi>Lewes,</hi> did tranſport himſelf cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in purple to S. Auguſtines, where the Court of Parliament had formerly been kept, concerning the Coronation of the Queene, and the former triumph. When being ſet in his Chaire of Iuſtice, he was proclaimed king in the preſence of the Queene mother, being ſet by his ſide, vailed ouer in a vayle of blacke Cypreſſe, aſsiſted with foure Cardinals, foure
<pb facs="tcp:4158:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
Peeres of the Church, ſundry Biſhops, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, &amp; ſome princes of the bloud, and other princes who were then reſident in Court, the Conſtable of France, diuers Dukes, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall of France, officers of the crowne, and gouernours of the prouinces, where was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by an act, pronounced by the mouth of the Lord chancelour, by the aduice of the cardinals, the princes, peeres, and Lords heereupon named and of this Court of parliament, that the Queene receaued the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Queene mother regent of Fraunce, for the gouernment of the king her ſonnes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, his kingdomes, and his needfull affaires. After which, the gates were opened, that the people might ſee the yong king in his throne. When Mounſiere <hi>Seruin</hi> the kings Attourney generall, made an admoniſhing Oration to the people vpon the buſineſſe in hand, and in eſpeciall of the good that France ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue by the gouernment of the ſaid Queene, concluding that what was paſt ſhould be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified in the prouinces, and withall requiring them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o pray, that God may preſerue vs our king <hi>Lewes.</hi> And that his age may make him gather the fruits of our obedience, wee do ſweare him ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ulnes of conſtancie
<pb facs="tcp:4158:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
and of zeale, that we find we haue more paine in the ſpeaking of it, then we know we ſhall haue in the executing of it.</p>
            <p>And to begin in good time, let vs in his glory pray that he may in good time come to the protection of Chriſt, and in this hope we muſt bee contributarie with teares on the Hearce of the dead King, ſince the will of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen doth leade vs thither, ſaying, that ſince he hath dealt with vs like a father and like a prince, we entreate of the diuine Maieſtie, that hauing eſtabliſhed him to be a ſhield to his people, it would pleaſe him to receiue him to his glory. And as hee forgaue them that had offended him, ſo he will forgiue him his offences, vſing his mercies ſooner, then his Iuſtice, that hauing had ſo many and ſo faire victories in the world, both in forraine Countries and at home, hee may bee yet victorious raigning in heauen, and hauing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed the peace of ſo flowriſhing an Empire, he may enioy the felicitie of the happy.</p>
            <p>After which, let vs offer our vowes and our ſuffrages, for the continuing proſperity both of the king and the Queene, that it may pleaſe God ſo to further and proſper the king,
<pb facs="tcp:4158:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
that he may hold his people vnder the yoake of his Commaundements, and ſo ſee him augment in perfection as in age, alwaies to bee beloued of his ſubiects, fauoured of his Allies, and feared of the Nations barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; that one day he may ſpread &amp; hang out his enſignes in the Land of Misbeleeuers, and that he may keepe the promiſes of his birth in the ouerthrow of the Ottomans.</p>
            <p>That the Queene aſſsiſted with the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity of the Counſell, may reape the reſt of the fruits of his vertues, that ſhe may inioy his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with ſo much proſperitie, that it may prooue to the aduancement of the king to the honour of her, and to the comfort of the people. That the atchieuements the which the dead king her huſdand held from heauen, may ſerue her for a Model and be the faire example for her to imitate, applying her ſelfe to the occaſions of them that haue moſt merite, and not of them that vſe moſt importunity: that ſhee may hearken to all mens requeſts but not to all mens flatteries, whereby all may haue occaſion to ſay, that ſhe is capable to raigne. That as the Moone holds her light, which ſhe hath borrowed of
<pb facs="tcp:4158:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
the Sunne; yet ſtild <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eth her Orbe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it vnto vs: So ſhe hath held the perfections, ſhee hath ſeene practiſed in the dead king, to ſerue herſelfe in his ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace, in her glory, to the profit of her ſonne and his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects. And alſo that as the Touch-ſtone that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oueheth the gold, the ſiluer and tryeth it, ſhe may keepe in properly this prudence and this goodneſſe which ſhe hath borrowed of his dead maieſtie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nour in Rome to haue returned the armie of his ſonne, which he had prepared for the ruine of his Country, and <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Medices,</hi> our Queene ſhall receiue a great praiſe of al the world to haue gouerned the ſtate of our king her ſonne, with ſo great wiſedome, that there ſhall bee no difference found in the raigne paſſed and the raigne to come, that no ſexe may hereafter ſpeak of the raigne of a woman more then of hers, ſeeing an others haue not preceded her by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; ſhe aduanced by merit, &amp; that the fayreſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the predictions of the effect; of her that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may ſee the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> time of her raigne through her ſorrow and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſees her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> through a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſay by Auguriſme that which you ſhall expect and we ioy in.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4158:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
